בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is ק"ה, Kuf Hey, 105,
and we pick up about eight lines from the top on the
two dots: חוץ מהשבת שוה פרוטה לקרן. chutz me’hashavat shaveh perutah la’keren.
So this is if a person has this obligation if he steals
and swears falsely, I mean if he steals he has to return
it but if he swears falsely he has this more so sort
of compelling obligation to chase after the guy and find him wherever
he is and return it. But the משנה Mishnah says that obligation
would no longer exist once the principal had gotten to be less
than a פרוטה. perutah. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara is going to
explore this idea of the מצוה mitzvah of השבה hashava in where
the principal is less than a פרוטה, perutah, but maybe there still
could be some obligation to return it. Okay, so let's take a
look. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Papa, said Rav Papa, לא שנו
אלא שאין גזילה קיימת. lo shanu ela she’ein gezeilah kayyemet. That idea
that you don't have any obligation and this is to run after
the guy remember is if the physical object is no longer present
and it's just a monetary obligation. A monetary obligation less than a
פרוטה perutah
is
not really a monetary obligation.
If what was stolen was already less than a פרוטה perutah to
begin with?
No, it was that doesn't matter. Could be that you stole a
basket of apples, you returned all of them and you had left
one in your house and that one remaining apple is less than
a פרוטה. perutah. Okay? So the original גזילה gezeilah was worth a
פרוטה perutah but now, or it could be the original גזילה gezeilah
was less than a פרוטה. perutah. It's true, it could be either,
maybe I'm jumping ahead of myself and thinking about the next case
in the גמרא. Gemara. So whether what's left is less than a
פרוטה perutah or whether the whole גזילה gezeilah was less than a
פרוטה, perutah, he doesn't have this obligation to run after the guy,
but that's only if the physical object isn't around. אבל גזילה קיימת,
aval gezeilah kayyemet, if the physical object is still around, צריך לילך
אחריו, tzarich leilech achrav, not just you have to return it but
you have to chase after him. Why? חיישינן שמא תייקר. chashinan shema
t’yaker.
We're concerned now I might have said because it's his object, you
know? It doesn't matter more than a פרוטה, perutah, less than a
פרוטה. perutah. It might be it doesn't have any dollars value, but
physically that's my object. Now that would be true, that would mean
why you can't hold it to yourself. Right? If Michael is holding
on to I don't know my paper clip, he can't say it's
less than a פרוטה perutah make me give it to you. I
mean it's my paper clip, you know? So I'm entitled for it.
Now maybe בית דין Beis Din would not hear the case. בית
דין Beis Din wouldn't hear a case less than a פרוטה. perutah.
But I still have a right to demand it from Michael. Okay,
so that's so you don't need to say that its value might
go up. But if I'm here and I want it back. The
issue is does Michael have a need to run after me and
to take the 1 train and spend three and a half dollars
or however much it is on the 1 train now to return
to me my paper clip, okay, which is less than a פרוטה.
perutah. So the answer, first answer is yes. Why? Because who knows?
The value of paper clips might go up. שמא תייקר. shema t’yaker.
And because it might worth... but that's a little strange. Wait till
its value go up and then you'll run after me. Okay, but
that's the initial response. איכא דאמרי, ika d’amri, others say, אמר רב
פפא, amar Rav Papa, לא שנא גזילה קיימת ולא שנא שאין גזילה
קיימת. lo shna gezeilah kayyemet velo shna she’ein gezeilah kayyemet. It doesn't
matter if the גזילה gezeilah is around or if it's not around,
even if he's holding on to the paper clip, אינו צריך לילך
אחריו. eino tzarich leilech achrav. He does not have to run after
me again. If it's still there and I'm around I can demand
it back, whether the court will hear the case is a different
issue. But does he have to run after me? No. He doesn't
have to run after me if it's less than a פרוטה perutah
even if it's still around. לשמא תייקר לא חיישינן. leshema t’yaker lo
chashinan. We're not concerned ahead of time maybe the value will go
up. If the value goes up then let him run after me
at that stage. Yes?
But as you've already alluded to this I think, this is something
fundamentally wrong here. In other words, in other words, the court won't
hear it because it's not worth their time. Right. And you don't
have to run after him because it's not שוה פרוטה. shva perutah.
Right.
But fundamentally it's not yours, it's mine, I want my paper clip
back. Right. He doesn't have
a moral right...
what? You'd settle for a paper clip? Oh
you know that's how much talk...
he does not have a moral right to keep it. That is
correct. Right.
So like that's absent. The only thing that's bothering me is that's
absent from the גמרא.
Gemara. Right, the גמרא Gemara doesn't make that explicit. Right, that's true,
the גמרא Gemara should be making that explicit.
What about the לא תגזול?
lo tigzol? Yeah, I don't know. It's a good question. Look, there's
another interesting question also which is if somebody steals less than a
פרוטה, perutah, are they over... are they over לא תגזול? lo tigzol?
You know, the רמב"ם Rambam interestingly says that if I'm remembering this
correctly, that if you wound someone you're over on a לאו, lav,
right? The לאו lav is לא יוסיף להכותו... lo yosif lehakkoto... פן
יוסיף להכותו מכה רבה. pen yosif lehakkoto makkah rabbah. So but you
don't do get מלקות malkus for it because it's ניתן לתשלומין, nittan
letashlumin, right? You you compensate the person. But the רמב"ם Rambam says
but if you wound a person less than a שוה פרוטה, shva
perutah, you do get מלקות, malkus, because there's no compensation and then
you're... מלקות malkus for transgressing the לאו lav ironically even though the
injury was less. But the רמב"ם Rambam never says that if you
steal less than a פרוטה perutah you get מלקות. malkus. Okay, now
that's...
that's less than... you know the רמב"ם Rambam was destroyed based on
that.
Oh there you go. So anyway, but presumably there's a difference that
a wound is an objective problem no matter how much the value
is whereas stealing less than a פרוטה perutah is not like you
really stole money. Okay, so it's fun. So that's an interesting question.
Is it even considered like you're עובר over on לא תגזול lo
tigzol or not? But yes, you are right, that I mean, I
guess if you have my object, I have a right to get
it back, but
the and the גמרא Gemara is right, I mean, no recourse, and
the גמרא Gemara isn't even addressing that basic right that I have,
whether I have recourse or not. That is true. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara continues. It says, but anyway, but if it's but
he certainly does not have to run after me if it's less
than a פרוטה prutah and we're not concerned the value will go
up. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, says רבא. Rava. גזל שלוש אגודות, Gazal
shalosh agudot, somebody stole three bunches, bunches of I don't know, of
carrots or whatever they stole, three bunches of parsley. Okay,
בשלש פרוטות beshalosh prutot and each bunch of parsley was worth a
פרוטה. prutah. והוזלו ועמדו על שתים vehuzlu ve-amdu al shtayim and now
the three bunches are worth two פרוטות. prutot. So each bunch of
barley is worth less than a פרוטה. prutah. Okay, but when I
stole it, I stole three פרוטות. prutot. Now, also let's imagine let's
say all the barley was lost. All the barley... why'd I say
barley, parsley... all the parsley was lost. How much do I owe
Michael who I stole it from? Before Michael was the גזלן, gazlan,
now I'm the גזלן, gazlan, I forget which way it works. Anyway,
how much do I owe Michael that I stole from? I owe
him three פרוטות, prutot, right? It doesn't matter that when they got
lost they were only worth two. כל הגזלנים משלמים כשעת הגזלה. kol
hagazlanim meshalmin kishat hagezeilah. Okay, so but if they're around, I have
to... I give him back the bunches of parsley. Alright, that are
now worth combined two פרוטות. prutot. Okay. והוזלו ועמדו על שתים. vehuzlu
ve-amdu al shtayim. אם החזיר לו שתים, im hehzir lo shtayim, now
I returned to Michael two bunches of barley. So this third bunch
is worth two-thirds of a פרוטה, prutah, right? Everybody with me? Right
now? Okay, so
אם החזיר לו שתים חייב להחזיר לו אחרת. im hehzir lo shtayim
hayav lehahazir lo aheret. I still have to give him the last
bunch. Now again, he has a right to demand it back whether
I you know, regardless, it's his, but the חייב להחזיר hayav lehahazir
presumably means I have to run after him, I have to find
him, I have a legal you know, it's more than just a
moral obligation, a legal obligation, I have to give him the last
one. Okay, even though it's less than a פרוטה. prutah. Now, part
of the to some degree that's not such a חידוש hiddush because
well, let's take a look. ותני טונא u-tani tuna and we taught
in our משנה Mishnah similarly. גזל חמץ ועבר עליו הפסח. gazal hametz
ve-avar alav ha-Pesah. If I stole חמץ hametz and now it was
worth a hundred dollars and now it's been פסח Pesah and it's
worth zero. אומר לו הרי שלך לפניך. omer lo harei shelcha lefaneicha.
I can give Michael back the חמץ hametz and say here, take
your חמץ hametz back. Okay, that seems like it gets me off
the hook. How's that relevant for our discussion here? We're speaking about
my obligation to return this bunch of parsley. So the גמרא Gemara
says the following. טעמא דאיתא בעיניה. ta'ama de-isa be-inei. The reason I'm
able to give Michael back the חמץ hametz which is worth zero
and get off my hundred dollar debt is because it's still present.
הא ליתא בעיניה, ha-leisa be-inei, if it's not present, אף על גב
דהשתא לאו ממונא, af al gav de-hashta lav mamona, even though right
now, okay, here's the point. I can give him something that's worth
zero and be exempt. But if that thing isn't around, I owe
him a hundred dollars.
I have to pay him what it was worth before.
כיון דמעיקרא ממונא הוה בעי שלומי. keivan de-me-ikara mamona hava bai shlumei.
Okay, I would have to pay him a hundred dollars if it
weren't around, but now that it's around, even though it's worth zero,
I have to give it back to him. Okay. הכא נמי אף
על גב דהשתא לא שוה פרוטה. hacha nami af al gav de-hashta
lo shaveh prutah. Here this bunch of barley isn't worth a
פרוטה. prutah. כיון דמעיקרא הוה שוה פרוטה בעי שלומי, keivan de-me-ikara hava
shaveh prutah bai shlumei, I have to give it to him. So
the analogy is the following, okay? By the חמץ, hametz, I owe
Michael... now you really could say is that if I stole a
hundred dollars worth of חמץ hametz from Michael, I owe him a
hundred dollars and the giving him the חמץ hametz is a way
off the hook. But why do we look at it that way?
Fundamentally, it's his חמץ. hametz. Okay, so I here have Michael's חמץ,
hametz, right? I don't owe him a hundred dollars yet. It starts
with the fact that I have his object. His object is worth
now zero dollars. Okay, do I have a חיוב hiyuv to return
his object? Yes. Now, why do I have a חיוב hiyuv to
return his object? Probably the reason is because if I don't return
the object, I got a חיוב hiyuv to pay him a hundred
dollars. Okay, so I did an act of גזילה gezeilah that was
a גזילה gezeilah of money, it was worth more than a פרוטה,
prutah, and that is compelling me to return this object. Either return
this object or pay him for the value that you stole. Similarly
here, the bunches of barley, because initially this one bunch was worth
a פרוטה, prutah, okay? I now have it that it's worth less
than a פרוטה. prutah. I have to return this less than a
פרוטה. prutah. It doesn't matter. You stole from him and you did
an act of גזילה. gezeilah. It was worth a פרוטה. prutah. That
is compelling you to make restitution. So that restitution has to take
place in one of two forms: either give him back the object
or give him the פרוטה. prutah. Okay, so in a way, you
know, if you emphasize the obligation, it's like wait, wait, how's this
similar to the חמץ? hametz? But look at it in the same
way as חמץ. hametz. Okay, I stole a פרוטה's prutah worth of
parsley, so I can say הרי שלך לפניך harei shelcha lefaneicha and
give him back the half פרוטה prutah worth because that's what it's
worth right now. And if I don't want to do that, then
I have to pay him for the פרוטה. prutah. Okay, so because
the גזילה gezeilah originally, thank you so much, because the original גזילה...
gezeilah... and that's what I got there is old, so thank you...
because the original גזילה gezeilah was a real גזילת ממון, gezeilas mamon,
it was a פרוטה, prutah, that obligates me to make restitution either
to pay the initial value or to return the object as it
is now regardless of what it's worth. Yes?
The גמרא's Gemara discussion says determining that somebody has to pay the
value at the time of the robbery.
Yes, if you're not returning the object itself.
That's the הרי שלך לפניך harei shelcha lefanecha discussion. Yeah, I realize
that's very unfair. Once again, but yes, but this is, but we've
seen this unfairness before. Yeah, yeah, but that is correct. Okay, so
that's point number one. There's cases where you have to return
פחות מפרוטה pachot miperutah when you stole more than a פרוטה perutah
or a פרוטה's perutah worth and this object is the original object
that you stole. Okay.
הבו ליה בטיסא havu lei b'tisa is analogous to גזלו.
gezelo. Exactly. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: הכא
דאיכא hacha de'ika okay fine. Now,
כיון דמעיקרא הוה שוה פרוטה kivan demeikara hava shaveh perutah בעי למהדר.
ba'ei lemeihdar. Now רבא Rava asks the following question: גזל שתי אגודות
בפרוטה. gazal shtei agudot beperutah. I originally stole two bunches of parsley,
I have to do something else, let's say
carrots. I stole two bunches of carrots, okay, בפרוטה beperutah and they
were worth a פרוטה perutah combined. והחזיר לו אחת מהן. vehachzir lo
achat mehen. And then I returned to Michael one of them. So
now the initial גזילה gezeilah was a פרוטה's perutah worth. Does that
mandate that I return this remaining bunch of carrots? Right, that's why
we're saying carrots. Does it demand that I return it? Now again,
what's missing from this גמרא Gemara and I keep on inserting and
maybe somebody disagrees with that is whether I have a חיוב chiyuv
to return it or not and whether the court will listen to
it or not. You know, I obviously it's Michael's carrots and I
shouldn't be holding on to them, but the question still is, right,
how much does that create this sort of, you know, legal obligation
for me to return it?
עד דמצטרף, ad demitztaref, right? In other words, you could say I
didn't steal a שוה פרוטה. shaveh perutah.
Well that, well, right, at the time, no, right, obviously at the
time you stole a שוה פרוטה. shaveh perutah. But the question here
is, my, even at the time, the remaining bunch of carrots was
worth less than a פרוטה. perutah. So as opposed to before when
originally the bunch of carrots was worth a פרוטה, perutah, now it's
less, but the fact that I stole this bunch of carrots which
was originally worth a פרוטה perutah compels me to make compensation either
by giving the פרוטה perutah or giving the carrot. Here, originally the
whole act was a שוה פרוטה, shaveh perutah, but I returned half
of it. What's left was never a שוה פרוטה. shaveh perutah. Am
I compelled to return it to Michael because it was part of
the initial גזילה gezeilah that was a שוה פרוטה shaveh perutah or
do I say because this piece of it was never שוה פרוטה,
shaveh perutah, there's nothing that compels me to return this object? Okay,
that's the question.
Because they're two separate objects? Yeah. Meaning if you stole a bar
of gold, I'm not going to say that that little left right
side, you know...
Well, that would be an interesting variation of רבא. Rava. Let's say
I stole one carrot and I broke it in half and then
the carrot was worth a פרוטה perutah and I returned you half,
right? Would that be different? Okay, that's a second-level question. Let's first
see his question when they were separate objects when I stole it.
Okay. So do we say like this: אמר ליה מי אמרינן amar
lei mi amrinan do we say השתא ליכא גזילה, hashta leika gezeilah,
now what's left in my hand is no longer considered a גזילה,
gezeilah, at least in terms of like there was no, it did
not have a minimum, minimum dollar value to it ever, even when
it initially was stolen. So there's nothing that compels me to return
it. או דילמא od dilma or do we say הא לא הדר
דגזילה דהוה גביה. ha la hadar degezeilah de hava gabeih. I didn't
return the גזילה gezeilah that was with me. I did not fully
return what I stole. I stole two bunches and I or two
carrots let's say and I only returned one. So maybe the fact
that initially I stole I haven't finished my obligation of returning. I
only returned half even though what's left with me is not worth
a פרוטה. perutah. Okay. הדר פשטה hadar pashtei then he in the
end sort of came to a conclusion, sort of, which was saying
גזילה אין כאן השבה אין כאן. gezeilah ein kan hashavah ein kan.
There is no
stolen object in my hands, it's no longer worth a פרוטה, perutah,
so there's no השבה. hashavah. Now what does that mean? It could,
the simple sense of that I think would mean therefore I have
no obligation, remaining obligation to return it. Okay. But the גמרא Gemara
understands that differently. The גמרא Gemara understands there's no גזילה gezeilah and
therefore I haven't fulfilled the מצוה mitzvah of
השבה.
hashavah. So because it's the same as the הבו ליה havu lei
case, same as the הבו ליה havu lei case.
What? Well let's take a look.
He kept one behind, he only returned two out of three. Right.
That's just a check?
It's not the exact same thing because here's this part was never
worth a שוה פרוטה. shaveh perutah.
Neither was the one that he held, held.
No, the in the earlier case when it was originally stolen it
was worth a שוה פרוטה. shaveh perutah. Right, the original case is
I stole three פרוטות. perutot. Yeah, exactly, exactly. Okay. So גמרא Gemara
says like this: One minute. גזילה אין כאן gezeilah ein kan if
this remaining carrot in my hand is not considered to be anymore
a stolen object or have enough value for us to be care
about it, השבה יש כאן hashavah yesh kan then it should mean
that I fulfilled my obligation of השבה hashavah because if there's nothing
left for me to do then I'm done. You know, why do
you say how can you say I didn't? don't have anything left
and I haven't fulfilled my
obligation. So הכי קאמר, hachi kama, yeah, we are saying that, אף
על פי שגזלה אין כאן, af al pi shegezeila ein kan, even
though you don't have any any stolen object left left with you
because it's not worth a פרוטה, prutah, מצות השבה אין כאן. mitvat
hashaba ein kan. You you still haven't really, you know, totally, you
know, exempted yourself, you have not really fulfilled the mitzvah of returning.
So this in a way strikes like strikes that middle sort of,
you know, place. It's basically saying on the one hand what you
have left is less than a שוה פרוטה. shaveh prutah. Okay,
you know, but... but nevertheless, you know, you have less than a
שוה פרוטה shaveh prutah and we can't sort of mandate you to
return it. But on the other hand, you haven't really fully fulfilled
the obligation of השבת גזלה hashavat gezeila because you didn't fully return
everything that you stole. Okay, so it's sort of trying to strike
this middle place. Let me just see something and just hold on
a minute.
Yeah.
תוספות Tosafot sort of deals with it, right? He says, right?
והנפקא מינה דלמא מעכב מצות השבה. vehanafka mina dilma me'akev mitvat hashaba.
Right, ומצות השבה מיהא לא קיים. umitzvat hashaba miha lo kiyem.
Right, on the one hand you didn't like have no legal obligation
left, on the other hand you didn't fulfill your מצות השבה. mitvat
hashaba. Right. Alright, so let's take a look. The Gemara is going
to have another similar case. Maybe it'll help us understand this, maybe
not.
Parallel, has nothing to do with גזילה. gezeila. ואמר רבא, ve'amar Rava,
Rava says, הרי אמרו, harei amru, they said, נזיר שגילח ושייר שתי
שערות. nazir shegilach veshayer shtei se'arot.
So at the end of the נזירות, nezirot, there's a מצוה mitzvah
to shave off all the hair of the head. So let's say
he shaves off all the hair, all the hair of the body,
whatever, anyway, but let's say he shaves off all the hair,
but he left two hairs left. לא עשה ולא כלום. lo asa
velo klum. That's not shaving off all the hair. Okay? One hair
is negligible, like one hair is like less than a פרוטה. prutah.
Two hairs is a פרוטה. prutah. Two hairs means that something substantive,
it's... okay, and therefore you have not finished shaving all the hair.
Okay, בעי רבא, ba'ei Rava, so now Rava asks the following question.
גילח אחת. gilach achat. Now you left two hairs over from shaving
this נזיר, nazir, and then you went back and you shaved one
of the two hairs, ונשרה אחת, venashra achat,
and the other one fell off. מהו? mahu? Did you... did you
fulfill your מצוה mitzvah of גילוח? giluach? Okay, so אמר ליה רב
אחא מדפתי amar lei Rav Acha midifti לרבינא, leRavina, בנזיר שגילח אחת
אחת קמיבעיא ליה לרבא? benazir shegilach achat achat kamiba'aya lei leRava?
Is Rava's question like let's say I shave by cutting each hair
individually? You know, it's like the old joke, you know, it says
I just got a haircut, I hope you got more than one.
So anyway, so you know, so
if you're shaving and you're cutting each hair individually, nobody thinks that's
not considered גילוח, giluach, that with every cut you have to cut
two hairs, right? You can cut an individual hair one at a
time. So if that's true, if this guy has two hairs left
and you cut one of
them... so therefore, since everybody would agree that you can cut each
hair individually as you're shaving off the hair of the נזיר, nazir,
so I shaved off every single hair of his, you know, 10,000
hairs and I left one... two, and then I went back and
I cut one of the two. So that's like two... like cutting
each one individually. I cut a thousand and then I cut one,
so that should combine the same way if I cut each one
individually it combines. So now I've cut all of his hairs except
one. So that's the מצוה mitzvah of גילוח, giluach, that's the מצוה
mitzvah of shaving, right? We said if I would have cut all
his hairs except one I would have been יוצא. yotzei. So what
I did is I cut all of his hairs except two and
then I cut one. So fine, at the end of the day,
I cut all the hairs except one. I should be יוצא. yotzei.
What's the question? You don't even need the last one to fall
off.
I would have thought that if the question would be he cut
everything except for two and then one fell off.
That's going to be the question, but that's not what we said
yet. So אמר ליה, amar lei, so he said back to him,
לא צריכא, lo tzricha, here's the case. The order is reversed. כגון
שנשרה אחת ואחר כך גילח אחת. kegon shenashra achat veachar kach gilach
achat. You're right. Okay, if you had cut all and left two
and then cut one more, you would have cut all except one
and you'd be יוצא. yotzei. But you cut all except two and
then of the remaining two one fell off. So now when you're
only cutting one, okay, you're not... is it considered an act of
גילוח giluach when there's less than two hairs? Two hairs in גילוח
giluach is like the שוה פרוטה shaveh prutah in, you know, in
money. Okay? So cutting off when you start with less than two
hairs might not be considered an act of גילוח giluach at all.
Okay, so what's the story there? מי אמרינן השתא מיהא ליכא שיעור?
mi amrinan hashta miha leika shiur? Do we say now, you know,
there's, you know, there's not a שיעור? shiur? Okay,
and therefore, you know, since there's not a שיעור shiur left, you're
יוצא yotzei the מצוה mitzvah of
גילוח? giluach? או דילמא האי לאו גילוח הוא דמעיקרא? o dilma hai
lav giluach hu dimeikara? Originally you didn't do the מצוה mitzvah of
גילוח. giluach. השיור ששיירת hashiyur sheshiyarta because originally you left over two
hairs, והשתא כי גילח לא הוי בידיה שתי שערות. vehashta ki gilach
lo havei beyadei shtei se'arot. Now when you did the shaving, there
was only one hair left. So you didn't do the גילוח giluach
originally, you didn't do an act of גילוח giluach now, it doesn't
matter that no hairs are left, you didn't do an act of
גילוח. giluach. Okay? So what happened? I don't know what, you'd have
to wait for the next bit. To grow back to go through
the whole process. תוספות Tosafot also says it could be according to
the way we פוסקין pas'ken גילוח giluach is not מעכב. me'akev. It's
sort of like the discussion before, you want יוצא yotzei the מצוה,
mitzvah, but it's not necessarily מעכב. me'akev. And if it is מעכב,
me'akev, you wait for it to grow back and you do it
again. Okay. הדר פשטה, Hadar pashta, so then he concluded, שער אין
כאן גילוח אין כאן. se'ar ein kan giluach ein kan. There's no
hair, so there's no גילוח. giluach. Okay. Similar phrase as before. Okay.
So what does that mean? שער אין כאן, se'ar ein kan, if
you say it's like there's no hair left, that sounds like there's
nothing left to be done, so it sounds like גילוח יש כאן.
giluach yesh kan. Then logically you should say you were יוצא yotzei
the מצוה mitzvah of גילוח. giluach. That's the logical
conclusion. Okay. Unless you say the even though, but without the even
though, if you start by saying, 'Oh, because there's no hair,' you're
expecting to say, 'And therefore there's nothing left to be done,' you're
expecting the end of that sentence to be 'Therefore you were יוצא.'
yotzei. So the גמרא Gemara says, no. הכי קאמר. Hachi kama. אף
על פי ששער אין כאן, Af al pi she'se'ar ein kan, although
there's nothing left to be done, nothing of substance, מצות גילוח אין
כאן, mitzvat giluach ein kan, you did not do the מצוה mitzvah
of גילוח giluach because
you didn't do an original act of גילוח giluach and you didn't
do an act of גילוח giluach at the end. And that's similar
to, now we understand that phrasing that works back to the השבת
פרוטה. hashavat peruta. Even though there's less than a פרוטה peruta left
and you would think you've done the מצוה mitzvah of השבה, hashava,
you haven't really done the מצוה mitzvah of השבה. hashava. Now, does
that mean that I'm obligated to return it? It doesn't sound that
way. It sounds like it's some, you know, interesting interim space where
you're a little caught in between or whatever. You might have a
moral obligation, whatever, but you weren't יוצא yotzei the מצוה mitzvah of
השבה hashava because now because you've not fully returned what you stole.
It sounds like they're teasing out and eluding very closely to the
moral obligation.
Right. Although here there's not a moral obligation, but yes,
by defining the limits of the legal obligations, what's left over is
the moral obligation being you should do but we can't constrain you
to do it in any in any way.
Right, right. That is what it sounds like going back to the
גזילה gezeila case.
That is correct.
David, did you want to share something?
Oh, I was just going to say there was a disagreement whether
he has to let it all grow back then.
Oh, grow back, yeah. רש"י Rashi says he doesn't have to. Aha,
aha. Right. So it's like a question like what are you doing
when you can't do the מצוה, mitzvah, right. What do you do
for a נזיר's Nazir balls?
You don't have to pay the barber, right, because he didn't do
his job. What? You don't have to pay the barber.
There you go. Well, that's interesting, yeah.
And רש"י Rashi says that he doesn't have to wait for the
פרוטה peruta but then he's able to bring the קרבן? korban?
Yeah.
It's an interesting question. I mean, there's two parts of that question.
It's sort of like the גילוח giluach question. Can you,
if you, if he was נשבע, nishba, right, because the גמרא, Gemara,
it's the משנה Mishnah started with the case of the השבת פרוטה,
hashavat peruta, case that a person took a שבועה shvua and then,
you know, what type of obligation that creates to run after the
guy, and then part of that is bringing a קרבן korban and
a חומש, chomesh, you know, when the גמרא Gemara got to the
question of, did you do the מצות השבה, mitzvas hashava, it doesn't
seem like it's talking specifically about the שבועה shvua case. But David
is asking in the case of a שבועה, shvua, I took a
שבועה shvua to Michael that I didn't steal his two carrots, okay,
and then I admitted, you know what, I did and I returned
one of the carrots and not the other one, can I go
ahead and I can bring my קרבן? korban? You right, that's a
sort of, so that's an interesting question. That's a two-part question. One
part is whether the payment of the קרן, keren, we haven't discussed
this, whether the payment of the קרן keren have to take place
before the קרבן korban is brought. Now actually the simple sense is
that it does, because going back to the משנה Mishnah that says
I have to run, well but the question is is the order
מעכב. me'akev. The משנה Mishnah that says I have to run after
you, the גמרא Gemara didn't say it but I think both רש"י
Rashi and תוספות Tosafot say that until I've run after you I
can't bring the קרבן. korban. One minute, one minute, one minute. The
קרבן korban is תלוי taluy on the גילוח.
giluach. Anyway, anyway, that's a good
question what רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot say
basically, תוספות Tosafot says
it for example, where's תוספות? Tosafot? אבל נותנים לשליח בית דין, Aval
notnim l'shliach beit din, the end of that תוספות Tosafot says on
ק"ג עמוד א', kuf gimal amud aleph, he says, דמפרישין לשליח בית
דין דיש לו כפרה מיד ואין צריך להמתין עד שיגיע ליד הנגזל.
d'mafreshen l'shliach beit din d'yesh lo kapara miyad v'ein tzarich l'hamtin
ad she'yagia l'yad hanigzal. So it sort of suggests the idea that
you know, do you have to wait till the guy gets it
before you can continue on and bring your קרבן. korban. Anyway, I
have to look into that. I don't remember offhand. Okay, so number
one, number one, that's a good question, like, do I have to
wait till the guy, do I first have to give back the
money before I the guy brings the קרבן. korban. Assuming that the
answer is yes, then you raise a very good point like in
this case, and that might be similar to this idea of the
גילוח giluach of the נזיר, Nazir, saying השבה אין כאן hashava ein
kan is make, it's a more weighty statement, it's sort of saying
like I can't bring my קרבן, korban, right? You know, בית דין
beit din might not be able to compel me to to return
it because it's less than a פרוטה, peruta, but I still haven't
done this מצוה mitzvah and maybe I can't proceed to the next
stage if it's a case of a שבועה. shvua. So that's a
very interesting read of this גמרא Gemara position. you same object. Does
that okay? Or is that— Well, that's a question going back way
to the beginning of בבא קמא, Baba Kamma, which is, like, can
you return in שוה כסף. shaveh kessef. But the answer is it
would be okay, but only based on current market values, right? It
would not be okay based on, you know, based on the original
value. If you stole something from me worth a thousand dollars, and
now it's worth five hundred, the market went down. And if it
was around, you could return me the object itself, but because it's
not around, you owe me a thousand dollars. You can't buy me
the object worth five hundred and give it to me, okay? Mean
exact same thing? Exact— doesn't matter. You owe me either the original
object itself or a thousand dollars. Okay, so if you want to
buy something and give it to me, it would only be based
on current market values. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay, ואמר רבא. V'amar Rava. Now Rava said, now this is— תוספות
Tosafot says it sounds similar to the previous cases, but it's really
not. It's not like you did half of something, but anyway, let's
take a look. Rava also said, הרי אמרו, harei amru, they said,
חבית שנקבה וסתמוה שמרים הצילוה. chavis shenikvah u'stamuha shemarim hitziluha. So there's
a whole question, רש"י, Rashi, תוספות, Tosafot, what this is talking about.
I'm going to say תוספות's Tosafot way. There's a principle of a
מוקף צמיד פתיל. mukaf tzamid pasil. Okay, if you have basically a
pottery vessel in a under a roof where there's a dead body,
so everything under the roof of the dead body becomes טמא. tamei.
You have some grain in the pottery vessel. If the pottery vessel
is covered with a tight seal—we're not going to define exactly what
defines a tight seal—but a tight seal, then the stuff inside is
טהור. tahor. Now let's say there's a hole in this pottery vessel,
enough for liquid to come out. Then it does not protect what's
inside of it. Okay, so you've got this חבית—whenever chavis חבית chavis
we tend to think of like a wood cask, but they had
pottery casks. You have a pottery cask, okay, and it's got a
hole in it, enough for liquid to come out, so it would
not save the wine in it, but some of the lees of
the wine that's in this have stopped it up, stopped up that
hole, effectively sealed the hole. Okay, so therefore that is considered like
the hole doesn't exist and everything in it does not become טמא.
tamei. All right, so let's take a look. So there's a hole
in the barrel, very good. So בעי רבא, ba'ei Rava, so Rava
asked, let's say rather than it being stopped up with lees of
the wine, you plastered it over. אגף חציה מהו? agaf chatziyah mahu?
Let's say you plastered over, okay, you know, part of the hole,
only half of the hole. So what's the story? Okay, now תוספות
Tosafot says, like, what does this have to do with the previous
discussions? It's not like there's a מצות השבה, mitzvas hashavah, מצות גילוח,
mitzvas giluach, or whatever. If the hole now is not big enough
to be a problem, it's not big enough to be a problem,
right? Who needs the whole hole to be filled, okay? The whole
hole, whatever. Anyway, okay. So anyway, but that's the גמרא's Gemara question.
How do you get that you plastered it over? Where's the... שמרים
הצילוה. shemarim hitziluha. No, so he asks another question. This is the
הלכה. halacha. If it's filled with the lees, it's filled. Forget the
lees. Let's say it's got a hole and you plastered half of
it. What's the story? Okay. אמר ליה רב יימר לרב אשי, Amar
lei Rav Yeimar l'Rav Ashi, לאו משנתינו היא זו? lav mishnateinu hi
zu? Isn't this our משנה? Mishnah? דתנן, d'tnan, חבית שנקבה וסתמוה שמרים
הצילוה. chavis shenikvah u'stamuha shemarim hitziluha. If it was, you know, the
lees stopped it up, then it saved the stuff inside. פקקה בזמורה,
p'kakaha b'zmora,
if you tried to seal the hole with a little twig, עד
שימרח. ad sheyimareyach. Then the filling a twig isn't enough, you have
to plaster it. I don't exactly get why a twig isn't enough
but the שמרים shemarim are. Is it because— what? Some of the
stuff that they use for just the normal seal is going to
be טיט tit anyway, so that— Right, but like, it's going to
be what? It's going to be טיט tit anyway. טיט. tit. Right.
Right, but I don't understand, why is— why is the stopping up
of the— of the gook of the grapes enough without plaster, but
when you use a twig you need to plaster? Is it that
somehow because the grapes is seen as natural and this is something
external, or is it because it just the grapes is, you know,
is tighter by itself and this is not as tight? I don't
know what the difference is, but anyway, you have to actually plaster
it. היו בה שתים. Hayu bah shtayim. Now let's say there were
actually two twigs, like it was a big hole and you needed
to bring two twigs to seal it off. עד שימרח מן הצדדים,
ad sheyimareyach min hatzedadim, you have to sort of plaster, you know,
I— the way I would think about this is like masking tape—
right? You have to plaster it on the sides to like keep
it, you know, you know, keep it so that it doesn't, you
know, get pushed out by the wine. ובין זמורה לחבירתה, u'vein zmora
l'chaveiratah, you have to plaster between the twigs itself. Okay. Now, so
what's— how is this relevant? He says look, טעמא דמרח. ta'ama d'mareyach.
The only reason that works, why do you need two twigs? One
twig should seal half the hole, assuming the hole is minimum size.
Okay. So you see that that only works because you plastered it.
הא לא מרח לא. ha lo mareyach lo. And if not plastered,
no. אמאי? amai? Why not? תהוי כאגף חציה. tehei k'agaf chatziyah. It
should be like you plastered over half the hole. So who needs
two twigs and to plaster between them even if you didn't plaster?
between them, you know? You filled up enough of the hole. So
אמרינן *Amrinan*. הכי השתא *Hachi hashta*? What kind of comparison is that?
התם *Hatam* אי לא מרח לא קאי אגב חבריה *ei lo marach
lo ka'ei agav chavreia*. If you don't plaster between the twigs, neither
of the twigs are going to stay. You need the whole thing
to seal it. It's not because you need every hole to be
filled, it's because to maintain the, you know, the fix, you know,
you need to plaster everything. הכא אגב פלגיה *Hacha agav palgeia*, but
if you plaster half of it, מיקם דקאי קאי *mikam dekaei kaei*.
That part that you've done will stay. So the fact that there
you need to do the whole thing, that's just so that it's
a permanent fix. But if you do a permanent fix on half
the hole, that's my question. And we don't have an answer. But
תוספות *Tosafot* says like what's the question? The hole isn't big enough
anymore. Okay, moving on. ואמר רבא Rava, *Ve'amar Rava*. הרי אמרו *Harei
amru*. Behold they said, גזל חמץ Chametz ועבר עליו הפסח *gezel chametz
ve'avar alav haPesach*, אומר לו הרי שלך לפניך *omer lo harei shelcha
lefanecha*. We saw that before. You stole חמץ Chametz, *chametz*, it's worthless
now, but you can say הרי שלך לפניך *harei shelcha lefanecha* and
get off of your obligation. בעי רבא Rava *Ba'ei Rava*. So רבא
Rava *Rava* asked, נשבע עליו מהו *nishba alav mahu*? Oh, here's a
great question. Okay, I steal, I'll steal it from David, I steal
from David his חמץ Chametz *chametz* right before פסח Pesach. *Pesach* worth
a thousand dollars. Now it's worthless. But I can, so if it's
not around, I pay him a thousand dollars. If it is around,
I just give it to him. David comes in and says Dov,
what did you do? You stole my חמץ Chametz *chametz*. And I
said חס ושלום *chas veshalom*, I'll take a שבועה Shevuah *shevua*. Okay,
I take a שבועה Shevuah *shevua* and then I admit, you know
what, you're right, I stole your חמץ Chametz *chametz*. Okay, so do
I have to, does it have all the consequences of taking a
שבועה Shevuah *shevua* on a monetary obligation where I pay a חומש
Chomesh *chomesh*? First of all, what's a חומש Chomesh *chomesh*? A חומש
chomesh *chomesh* of the original value, a חומש *chomesh* of the value
now? But do I bring a קרבן Korban *korban*? Why? Because what
did my שבועה Shevuah *shevua* do for him? Did my שבועה Shevuah...
*shevua* steal anything from him? If I hadn't taken my שבועה Shevuah
*shevua*, I would have given him worthless חמץ chametz, *chametz*. So normally
my שבועה Shevuah *shevua* effectively is stealing from somebody, preventing somebody from
getting the money that's coming to them. Here, the only thing the
שוא שבועה Shevuah *shav shevua* is doing is preventing him from getting
a bunch of worthless חמץ chametz, *chametz*. Is that a שבועה Shevuah
*shevua* on ממון *mamon* that leads to all of the obligations? That
question clear? Okay. So מהו *mahu*? What do we say? מי אמרינן
*mi amrinan*, do we say no, maybe I am stealing money from
David? Why? Because if the חמץ chametz *chametz* would get stolen or
lost, I'd have to pay him the thousand bucks. So ממונא קכפר
ליה *mamona kachafar lei*. So my שבועה Shevuah *shevua* is denying a
monetary claim. Okay, because it is possible that his claim against me
will translate into money. You could even say it in a different
way. Maybe he has a monetary claim against me to begin with,
but I can get out of it by returning the חמץ chametz.
*chametz*. That, but I think that that's not conceptually correct. Fundamentally my
obligation is to return the object that's stolen. If it's not around,
then I owe you its value. Okay, but nevertheless, even though now
I'm not denying you anything of value, but because it might, your
claim against me might translate into real money if I don't have
the חמץ chametz *chametz* anymore, then I am denying you a monetary
claim. That's one way of saying
it.
Okay. Did he mention a barrel? We figured out what the barrel
was having to do with anything?
No. Okay, we're moving on beyond that. או דילמא *o dilma*, or
do we say השתא מיהת הא מנח *hashta meihat ha manach*? No,
right now the חמץ *chametz* is still around and I can return
it. ועפרא בעלמא הוא *ve'afra be'alma hu*, and it's dust, it's worthless,
like you said כעפרא דארעא *ke'afra de'ara*. Actually if you said כעפרא
דארעא *ke'afra de'ara* it wouldn't be worthless anyway. It is pretty funny,
we have the phrase עפרא
בעלמא *afra be'alma*, which is the phrase you say by ביטול חמץ
*bitul chametz* everywhere. ולא כפר ליה ממונא *velo cafar lei mamona*. Right
now I'm only denying you your right to worthless חמץ *chametz*. So
right now I'm not stealing anything from you. Okay, so מילתא דאיבעיא
ליה לרבא *milta de'ibaia lei leRava*, so that was the question. That's
a fascinating question. פשיטא ליה לרבה *pishita lei leRabbah*. To רבה *Rabbah*
the answer was obvious. דאמר רבה *De'amar Rabbah*, because רבה *Rabbah* said,
שורי גנבת Shori ganavta. *shori ganavta*. David comes to me and says
Dov, you stole my ox. והוא אומר לא גנבתי *vehu omer lo
ganavti*. No, I didn't steal it. מה טיבו אצלך *mah tivo etzlecha*?
So what's it doing in your yard? שומר Shomer חנם אני עליו
*shomer chinam ani alav*. What are you talking about? I was watching
it for you. Okay, so basically what happened was and then I
take a שבועה Shevuah. *shevua* that I did not steal it, that
I'm only a שומר shomer חנם *shomer chinam*. And I'm lying, I
did steal it. Am I חייב Chayav, *chayav* to him? Like I'm
not, I'm not going to not give it back to him, even
according to my claim I'm saying I'm a שומר *shomer*. So what
type of a stealing was involved in
my false שבועה Shevuah *shevua*? So רבה *Rabbah* said חייב Chayav *chayav*.
I am חייב Chayav, *chayav* for all of the קרבן Korban *korban*
and everything. Why? שפטר עצמו מגניבה ואבידה *shepatar atzmo migneiva va'aveida*. Because
when I said I'm only a שומר חנם *shomer chinam* and I
took a שבועה Shevuah *shevua*, I was actually exempting myself from a
degree of liability. Because at the time between our little fight and
me returning it, let's say it died. Okay, if I was a
גזלן Gazlan, *gazlan*, I'd have to pay you for it. A גזלן
Gazlan, *gazlan* doesn't matter if it's an אונס Oness, *ones*, because I
stole I owe you. the value based on the time of stealing
it. But if I'm a שומר and it died, I would be
exempt. So since my שבועה shvua that I'm only a שומר exempts
me from possible liability, that is a שבועה shvua, that is getting
me out of a possible monetary claim that you have against me.
Right, or a possible claim you have against me. So if even
though if now I'm not denying you any money, if it's possible
that it's exempting me from some obligation, then it is a שבועה
shvua. that I would bring a קרבן Korban for. So similarly by
the חמץ on פסח. Right now I'm only denying you worthless חמץ,
but under certain circumstances that the חמץ isn't around, I'm denying you
a thousand dollars. So in that case it is a... so because
of that possibility for רבא, Rava. it's a שבועה shvua. that would
have all the consequences of bringing a קרבן Korban. and so on.
This isn't going to be adjudicated case by case. It doesn't matter
whether the חמץ exists or not, if you took the false שבועה...
shvua no, the חמץ definitely exists now and the ox definitely exists
now, but because of a possible future, whether that future materializes or
not, this שבועה shvua is a denying of a monetary claim. Okay,
interesting. Based on a lie.
Right, because I am lying and through my שבועה shvua I'm lying
and denying you a possible monetary claim against me, that שבועה shvua
obligates me to bring the קרבן Korban. and to add the חומש
and all of that. Okay, so now, or I say שומר שכר
אני עליו. Shomer Sachar ani alav. No, I didn't steal it, I'm
only a paid watch person. So חייב, Chayav. I still have to
pay you. Why? שפטר עצמו משבועה מתה. Shepatar atzmo mishvuah metah. Even
that case, I'm exempting myself from a level of liability. If I
was a גזלן, gazlan, I'd be חייב Chayav. even if it broke
its leg or died suddenly even if it was not something I
could control... I'm sorry, if I was a גזלן, gazlan. I'd be
חייב, chayav yes, even if it was something I couldn't control. But
as a שומר שכר, Shomer Sachar, if it's an אונס, Oness, I'm
exempt. So because I am exempting myself from a possible liability, that
שבועה shvua obligates... you know, is a שבועה shvua that gets me
out of...
that is a type of a stealing through a שבועה. shvua Or
wait a minute, even though I say שואל אני עליו, Shoel ani
alav, even if I claim I'm a borrower, and a borrower is
liable for אונס, I still and I'm swearing falsely, I still have
to do all the consequences because even that is denying you your
rights, you know, some of your monetary claims. חייב. chayav. שפטר עצמו
ממיתה מחמת מלאכה. Shepatar atzmo mimita machmat melacha. Even a שואל, Shoel,
if something breaks in the normal course of use, is exempt. Okay,
so it's an interesting הלכה Halacha by a שואל. Shoel. Right, if
a lightning strikes my... the cow that I borrowed from you, I'm
חייב. chayav But if as I'm using the cow, you know, through
normal use, it collapses and dies, I'm פטור. Patur. Okay, so that
we can have a whole discussion about that when we do it
in בבא מציעא. Bava Metzia. But because there is some exemption that
a שואל Shoel has, by claiming I'm a שואל, Shoel, I get
myself out of a hypothetical liability that could occur in some small
number of cases. That is enough to say that
that's a שבועה shvua that's מחייב Mechayev me a קרבן. Korban. Now
what I don't know, what רבא Rava isn't saying is, how much
money do I have to pay you? When I do a שבועה
shvua to false... to falsely deny you a claim that you have
against me, so if I'm saying like you say I stole a
hundred dollars and I say no and I'm lying, I pay you
a hundred dollars plus a חומש plus a קרבן. korban If you
say that's my cow worth a hundred dollars and I say no,
I didn't steal it, I'm only a שומר חינם, Shomer Chinam, a
שומר שכר, Shomer Sachar, and I'm lying, how much do I pay
you? Right? What, you know, do I pay you the value that
somebody would be willing to accept to be exempt from that degree
of liability? Right? I wasn't stealing the whole hundred dollar cow from
you. So I don't exactly know how much I would pay, but
I would certainly have to bring a קרבן. korban. And that's, you
know, so that's a definite consequence of this. It's not dealing with
what is the monetary liability here. You had a question though?
It's just interesting that the תלמוד Talmud keeps it totally within the
litigation between people. In other words, they didn't say well you took
a שבועת שוא. Shevuat Shav. Right, like that...
that's not a בבא קמא-ish Bava Kamma issue. If you want to
go ahead and figure out how many
איסורין Issurin you overthrew, we'll get to it... go look at מסכת
שבועות. Masechet Shevuot. But you are right, you know, that it is
very funny the way the גמרא's Gemara tend to be like, you
know, single out one lens on it. Right, you would really expect
in a... you know, it's always an interesting question which is like,
what is the significance of the fact that הלכה Halacha is religious
law? When you're dealing with, you know, בין אדם לחברו bein adam
l'chavero areas, when you're dealing with like monetary issues, you know, is
the fact that it's religious law make it somehow different? And you
would expect the answer to be well yes, because then there's going
to be a moral component to the discussion, you know, a religious
question of the violation. And every now and then, you know, you
have that, like you have about like, you know, when the גמרא
Gemara discussed about חסידים ראשונים Chasidim Rishonim would put away, you know,
bury or burn, you know, their glass broken glasses so people wouldn't
get injured. But that seemed to be like oh, here's a nice
thing to do. It didn't seem to be like part of the
actual
legal discussion as well. We would expect more discussions of moral mandates
or of questions of religious violation. In the end, isn't this person
admitting that he actually did steal it? Yes, and then he admits.
So right, so then why doesn't he have to pay the same
as if he was saying it was a hundred dollars? Doesn't he
have to pay? No, because I wasn't stealing the whole cow, I
was only denying you a level of liability, right?
When I said I was a שומר חינם shomer chinam and
really I was a גזלן, gazlan. was I trying to steal the
whole cow away from you? No. No.
Yes, but the question is what's a שבועה shvua is... of course
I return the cow. I say I'm a שומר חינם, shomer chinam,
I'm really a גזלן. gazlan Then I admit I was lying. So
of course I return the cow, okay. Now I pay a fifth
because of my false שבועה, shvua right? A fifth of what? A
fifth of the value of the cow? But the fifth is because
I swore falsely and in my swearing falsely I was stealing something
from you, right? I was denying. But I wasn't denying you the
whole cow in my שבועה. shvua, Okay, I'm just saying nevertheless. I
understand that I stole the whole... that's why I returned the whole
cow because I stole the whole cow. But my question is a
fifth of what? A fifth of the cow? But the fifth is
only coming because of the שבועה. shvua I don't want to belabor
the point, but okay, I think it is a question. Okay, so
let's go on. The גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. אלמא, Alma,
so you see that Rabbah holds, אף על גב דהא קאים, af
al gav de-ha ka'im, even though the object is there, okay, and
therefore I'm not really in that case the cow and I'm not
denying you the whole cow, כיון דמגנב ממונא קכפר, keivan de-mignav mamona
ka-kafer, since in the possibility the
cow would get stolen, my שבועה shvua. is denying you the right
to collect. So it's not right now my שבועה shvua is not
denying you anything, just come pick up your cow, I'm saying I'm
a שומר חינם. shomer chinam. But since it's denying you the right
to collect in a certain circumstance that might occur, so הא נמי
ממונא קכפר, ha nami mamona ka-kafer, here too though it's considered like
I'm denying you that money because of that possible future. And the
language of the גמרא Gemara sounds like it sounds like I'm denying
you the whole cow and I would pay a fifth to the
whole cow, going back to my question. Anyway, but that's enough that
it's denying you that possible future possibility. So הא נמי ha nami
here too by the חמץ, אף על גב דעפרא בעלמא הוא, af
al gav de-afra b-alma hu, even though right now my שבועה shvua
is only denying you collecting dust, worthless חמץ, כיון דמיגנב בעי שלומי
ליה, keivan de-mignav bayei shlumei leh, since were the חמץ to be
stolen I would have to reimburse you, so ממונא מעליא, mamona ma'alya,
you'd have to pay like real cash, so הא נמי ממונא קכפר,
ha nami mamona ka-kafer, my שבועה is not saying oh the שבועה
did nothing, I only denied you worthless חמץ. No, my שבועה denied
you the possibility of collecting the full thousand dollars were the חמץ
to be stolen. And therefore that type of a שבועה comes with
its חומש and comes with its קרבן korban and the whole thing.
That's at least Rabbah's position. Rava doesn't know, but that's Rabbah's position.
Okay, so יתיב רבא, yasiv Rava, so now Rava was sitting or
some have the גירסא girsa Rabbah just to make things confusing. As
Shamma Friedman has pointed out, you know, the גמרא Gemara is very
clear there's Rabbah and Rava, you know, and we know the difference
because of the ה hey and the א, aleph, and then sometimes
you always see these changes of גירסאות girsa'ot because things get a
little confused. Anyway, I think Shamma Friedman has pointed out that in
the original manuscripts they were not מדקדק medakdek in how they spelled
the names, like it was just, you know, there was no consistency
in spelling. So therefore what exists... that's the whole way we tell
the difference between who we're talking about. Okay, so
יתיב
רבא וקאמר לה שמעתא,
yasiv
Rava ve-kamar la-shma’ata, Rava was sitting over and telling over this discussion.
איתיב רב עמרם אמר ליה לרבא, Eisiv Rav Amram amar leh le-Rava,
and he was telling he doesn't know whether this type of a
שבועה is a good שבועה and you know it would מחייב mechayev
you, but Rabbah says it definitely would מחייב mechayev you. So Rav
Amram asked on Rava, but really it's a question
on
Rabbah who says that the שבועה is מחייב. mechayev. וכחש, Ve-kichash, we
have this מדרש הלכה. midrash halacha. וכחש בעמיתו בפקדון או בתשומת יד
או בגזל או עשק את עמיתו, Ve-kichash ba’amito b-pikadon o bi-tsumas yad
o ve-gazel o ashek et amito, this is the פסוקים psukim by
when you swear falsely. ונשבע על שקר והיה כי יחטא Ve-nishba al
sheker ve-hayah ki yecheta etc., etc., you know, so it says I
forget the end of the פסוק. pasuk. Anyway, והשיב את הגזלה אשר
גזל... ושלם אתו בראשו וחמשיתו יסף עליו לאשר הוא לו יתננו ביום
אשמתו. ve-heshiv et ha-gezelah asher gazal... ve-shilam oto b-rosho va-chamishito yosef alav
la’asher hu lo yitnenu b-yom ashmato. That's the whole thing at the
end of פרשת ויקרא, Parshat Vayikra, okay, and it starts by saying
you denied somebody, you know, something that you had of theirs. וכחש
בה, Ve-kichash bah, פרט למודה בעיקר. prat le-modeh b-ikar. So you have
to deny the whole object, says this מדרש הלכה, midrash halacha, to
exclude the case when you basically conceded that that object belonged to
the person, essentially Rabbah's case. כיצד, Keitzad, what's the case? שורי גנבת.
You say hey you stole my ox. הוא אומר לא גנבתי. Hu
omer lo gnavti. No, I didn't steal it. מה הוא עושה אצלך.
Ma hu oseh etzlecha. So what's it doing by you? אתה מכרתו
לי. Atta macharto li. Yeah, you sold it to me. אתה נתתו
לי במתנה. Atta netato li be-matanah. You gave it to me as
a gift. אביך מכרו לי. Avicha macharo li. Your father sold it
to me. אביך נתנו לי במתנה. Avicha netano li be-matanah. Your father
gave it to me as a gift.
אחר פרתי רץ. Achar parati ratz. You know, it ran after my
cow, it just followed my cow into my yard, okay. Your VCR
followed my VCR. I don't know what, okay, anyway, ממילא אתא. Mimela
ata. I keep on saying VCR,
nobody has a VCR anymore. I think they said that they stopped
out that manufacturing, like nowhere in the world do they anymore manufacture
VCRs. Anyway, okay.
Right after my laptop, right after my laptop.
Yeah, exactly. Your laptop ran after my laptop.
Okay, ממילא בידי. Mimela beyadi. It just it just came to me
on its own. טועה בדרך מצאתיה. To'eh baderech metzatih. I just found
it wandering on the way. Or שומר חנם אני עליה, Shomer chinam
ani aleha, שומר שכר אני עליה. Shomer sachar ani aleha. No, I'm
a שומר on it. I didn't steal it. שואל אני עליה. Shoel
ani aleha. I'm a borrower. Now in all those last cases when
he says you gave it to me as a gift, I really
am trying to steal it from you and the גמרא Gemara is
going to go back and ask about that. But all the last
cases I'm not denying that it's yours. I'm denying that I stole
it, but I'm not denying that it's yours. Okay, so am I
and I take a שבועה and I say I did not steal
it, it just followed me here. Okay, so am I so do
I am I חייב or not? So the מדרש הלכה Midrash Halacha
says ונשבע והודה, Venishba vehoda, I swear and then I admit. יכול
יהא חייב, Yachol yehei chayav, maybe I'm חייב. תלמוד לומר וכיחש בה,
Talmud lomar vechichesh ba,
you deny it. פרט למודה בעיקר. Prat lemodeh beikar. It's to exclude
the case when you conceded that it really is yours and you're
just getting out of some liability, right? By saying that it just
wandered into my yard, I'm saying if it dies suddenly, I'll be
exempt. It's רבא's Rava case. So I'm not denying you that it's
your cow, but I'm denying a level of liability that I have
by claiming that I'm not a גזלן. gazlan. And this ברייתא braita
says you don't have to pay. That contradicts רבא. Rava רבא Rava
said you do have to pay and you do bring a קרבן.
korban אמר
ליה תדורא. Amar leh tadura. He said to him like this is
nonsense or I don't know how they translate that. Scatterbrain! That's how
they translate it. Scatterbrain! Okay,
כי תניא ההיא. Ki tanya hahee. I know, it's so funny, they
they have these like harsh comments sometimes on really good questions. Even
if you're able to come up with an answer, it is a
good question.
Anyway, כי תניא ההיא. Ki tanya hahee. What's that ברייתא braita talking
about? דאמר ליה הילך. De'amar leh heilach. No, no, no. That ברייתא
braita is you know David comes to me and says, 'Hey, what's
my cow doing in your you stole my cow!' And I said,
'No, it just wandered here.' So, and I say, 'I'll swear to
you I didn't steal it! Okay, take it back and I'll swear
to you I didn't steal it.' Ah, I said, 'Take it back!'
If at the moment I am sort of saying, or even if
I don't hand it to you, I say, 'I swear that I
did not steal it and you can come take it at any
time, it's right here, just take it from me and I'm swearing
to you I did not steal it.' So, if you are able
to pick it up at this moment, right, I am not denying
you anything. Meaning it's not even I'm not even getting out of
a liability of it might drop dead. You know, there's nothing I'm
getting out of because I'm basically in this moment I'm returning it
to you. Okay, so in this case, there's nothing I'm getting out
of through my oath. דאמר ליה הילך. De'amar leh heilach. I say,
'Just take it!' Okay, in that case, my oath isn't getting me
out of anything.
כי קאמינא. Ki ka'amina. When am I talking about? Now this makes
sense that it's רבא talking. When am I talking about that I
say your oath is מחייב mechayav you because you're getting out of
a liability, even though you're admitting that it's his? דקאי באגם. Dekai
be'agam. It's somewhere in the swamp. So so it's going to take
a day for us to go find it and pick it up.
So in that day that it's going to take us to go
get it, my oath is exempting me from liability for that day.
Okay, so the face of it is the ברייתא braita really does
contradict רבא and seems like when you concede the basic point you're
exempt. But רבא says no, if you're getting out of a liability
you're חייב to bring a קרבן korban and the whole thing and
the ברייתא braita is a special case when you returned it at
the moment. Alright, so now the גמרא Gemara says says fine. So
now we've reconciled. Now we have to go back to the first
part of the ברייתא, braita, which sounded like that a case of
conceding it was when I said you sold it to me or
your father sold it to me. How is that conceding that the
principal belongs to the person? You're saying I bought it. Okay, so
let's take a look. את מכרת לי. At macharta li. מאי מודה
בעיקר איכא? Mai modeh beikar ika?
If I say you sold it to me, how am I conceding
that it's yours, that the principal is yours? No, לא צריכא דאמר
ליה, Lo tzricha de'amar leh, what I'm saying to you is לא
נתתי לך דמיה. Lo natati lecha dameha.
You sold it to me but I haven't paid you for it.
What, you want it back? Take it back! I haven't paid you
for it anyway. Okay, so then I'm conceding it's yours because I'm
saying that it's not fully mine yet, that I haven't paid you
for it. שקול
תורך וזיל. Shkol torech vezil. Take it and take it and go.
Fine. את
נתת לי. At natata li. אביך נתנה לי. Avich natna li. Your
father gave it to me. מאי מודה בעיקר איכא? Mai modeh beikar
ika? How is that a conceding of the principal? Give means give
as a gift. So if I'm saying I got it as a
gift, how am I conceding that it's yours? So דאמר ליה, De'amar
leh, because I say to you, על מנת דעבדת לי נייח נפשא.
Al mnat de'avadat li niach nafsha. You gave it to me as
a gift because you were expecting you wanted me to do some
favor for you. ולא עבדי לך. Velo avdi lach. You know what?
I didn't do the favor. שקול תורך וזיל. Shkol torech vezil. Go
take it back. Now of course that's an interesting point because you
know again it's like there might not actually be a legal claim
you have against me. It's not like I'm selling it to you
on the condition. I mean is it like a real תנאי tnai
that you have for the gift or is it like anyway? But
even if I'm just sort of saying like I don't want you
to have any claim against me you were expecting. take it back.
Now of course that's an interesting point because again it's like there
might not actually be a legal claim you have against me, it's
not like I'm selling it to you on the condition. I mean
is it like a real תנאי tnai that you have for the
gift or is it like anyway but even if I'm just sort
of saying like I don't want you to have any claim against
me you were expecting me to do you a favor just take
it back. So since I'm saying take it back even in my
שבועה, even if though I'm taking a שבועה that I'm lying about
the circumstances, I'm not trying to keep it to myself. Okay, so
we have a circumstance where I'm conceding that it's yours, I'm telling
you go ahead, take it back, it's there, it's waiting for you,
but I'm not but I'm denying that I'm a גזלן and I'm
lying. Yeah.
So I thought that with most gifts we kind of assume that
you are doing it in order to get something back from it.
We do sort of assume that often that's what motivates people,
but here
it's a little bit more explicit or expected, and there's also the
question of is it reciprocity or is it
in expectation? Right? Is it because you did something in the past
or because I'm expecting something in the future?
What difference does it make if he's מודה בעיקר modeh be'ikar if
he's lying anyway?
Because the lie you don't bring a קרבן for a false שבועה.
You bring a קרבן for making a שבועה that's stealing something from
somebody. So and that's the whole question, are you stealing? Let's just
try to get a little bit further. It says like this: טעה
בדרך מצאתי, tauh baderekh metzatzi, למא, lema, איבעי לך להדורי לי. iba'i
lakh lehadurei li.
So if I say, "Oh no no no, I didn't steal it,
it was just I just found it wandering." So why didn't you
say, "No, the fact that you found it wandering and you knew
it was mine and you took it home, you're conceding you stole
it. What other... that's a גזלן." You know, rather than giving it
to you, I took it for myself. אמר אביי דשמואל Amar Abaye
de'Shmuel באומר שבועה אבידה מצאתי ולא הייתי יודע שישך שהחזרנה לך. be'omer
shvua aveda matzati veloh hayiti yodea she'ishakh shehakhziranah lakh.
No no no, I didn't realize it was yours. Now you're telling
me it's your cow? Oh, now I know whose it is! Take
it back, fine. Right, I wasn't trying to keep it, I didn't
know who it belonged to, I kept it at home.
That's a classic case.
Right, exactly. Until you figure out who it belongs to.
Exactly. תניא. tanya. Okay, let's just do this one last case. אמר
בן עזאי, Amar Ben Azzai, ג' שבועות הן, gimel shvuot hen, there
are three types of oaths. You come and you say to me
that I you know, I stole your cow. And I say
you know, "No, I didn't steal it," actually it was... or hold
on, let me just get this let me just get this straight.
Hold on one minute.
No no no, I'm sorry, you didn't say I steal it. You
say, you said to me, "Dov, have you like, you know, seen
my lost object? I lost my cow, have you seen it?" Now
actually what I actually did was like I actually did see it
and I took it for myself, okay, and then I'm going to
swear to you, "No I didn't steal it," and I'm lying. Okay.
So let's take a look. Oh actually no, I'm sorry, I messed
up the case. One more time.
Because we're moving to a case from a false שבועה to... you
know what, we're going to end here because it's going to take
me too long and we have two minutes left.
We never found out about the barrel. Okay, but we're going to
end here, we're going to pick up with the שבועות shvuot about
lost objects tomorrow.